Inventory of the Jerdone Family Papers 1753-1890, 1771-1845
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, 1753-1890. (Box 1-10)
  - Letters, 1830-1839., 246 items. (Box-folder 7-9)
    - Letters, 1834., 10 items. (Box-folder 8:1)
      - Philip Brooks, Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, near Pottiesvill[e], Virginia, 30 November 1834., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:1)
        Describes damage done to crops by rain; reports poor quality of crops; discusses some prices for corn.
      - Fr[anci]s Jerdone [Jr.], Pro[vidence] Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 5 December 1834., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:1)
        Discusses heavy rains and violent weather and damage incurred; discusses difficulty In grinding grain; lists mills damaged; reports poor quality of crops; other business.
    - Letters, 1835., 36 items. (Box-folder 8:2-3)
      - Mary B. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 6 April 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Describes his daughter; refers to her distress and the sale of her horse and slave; begs Jerdone to buy the slave [Philis], her favorite servant, which [John N.] Moss would then hire back; gives list of slave's good qualities; other family news.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 24 April 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Feels bill of sale for property need not be recorded at Court House since sold to Jerdone; will arrange bill of sale with Clayton [Coleman] when he arrives.
      - J. N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 1 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Refers to recent sale of property to him [William Jerdone] and final settlements; sends Phillis over to avoid her being taken by sheriff.
      - Nath[anie]l Thompson, Pottiesville, [Louisa County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, n.p., 2 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Proposes means for Mr. John Moss to pay off his debts.
      - Francis Jerdone, Jr., Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 8 May 1935., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Discusses crops and prices; relates recapture of runaway slaves and resistance by one to capture; refers to poor condition of mill and attempts at restoration; refers to sale of horses; other family news.
      - W[illia]m K. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 8 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Inquires about matter of "brother John's man Dabney" and whether the deed of trust on him is good.
      - Charles James Thompson, Richmond, [Virginia] to his uncle, Francis Jerdone Sr., Louisa County, [Virginia], 10 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Informs of the death of his father, Charles Thompson; requests Jerdone to make arrangements; requests presence of Mr. Bower to read service and John Smith and family.
      - Jno. N. Moss, n.p. to W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 15 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Requests copy of household property given to Mr. Winston.
      - P. B. Winston, Jr., Louisa [County, Virginia] to W[illia]m Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa [County, Virginia], 21 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Reports settlement on Moss affair; reports slaves will be sold as soon as possible, which is 28th of May.
      - Mary B. Moss, Louisa County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 24 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Reports health of Maria Clayton; expresses sympathy for Jerdone's tooth "affliction"; reports brother John's visit; refers to Jerdone's daughter.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 24 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Refers to advertisement for sale of Moss property.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania [County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 31 May 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Feels should sell slaves for cash; expresses sorrow for Mrs. Moss' situation and hopes to visit next Tuesday.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 2 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Reports amount of sale; relates story of his excitement on that day over a man's accusation that he was dishonest; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 6 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Offers horse if needed; refers to his bad cold; refers to meeting at Court House.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Reports "carry-all" has arrived to bring slaves to court; asks if they should leave that day or wait until the next morning.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia]. 10 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Suggests that William and John Jerdone might buy a slave [Dabney] from him.
      - Jno. N. Moss, n.p. to W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 10 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Reports no need to buy articles for him as he cannot use them.
      - Nathaniel Thompson, Louisa [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 10 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Asks him and Mr. Coleman whether they will purchase goods which are listed.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 11 June 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Discusses auction of Moss' slaves and his purchase of one [named Dabney]; refers to clearing of accounts by Coleman and Thompson; other family news.
      - Clayton Coleman, Roxbury, [New Kent County, Virginia] to W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 20 June 1835. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Discusses attempt to sell Dabney; discusses his health; refers to crops and weather; refers to other business.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 25 June 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:2)
        Sends two shoats [little weaned pigs]; reports visit by sheriff; refers to health.
      - Mary B. Moss, Mill Creek to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 31 July 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Discusses family health; worries that their health is not improving; asks for any left over tomatoes; other family news.
      - Mary B. Moss, Mill Creek to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 6 August 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Reports daughter Maria has recovered from her illness; glad to hear of Clayton's safe arrival; other family news.
      - W[illia]m D. Taylor, Taylorsville to Francis [Jerdone, Jr.] and William Jerdone, near Pottiesville, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 August 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Recommends two men for the position of manager of the forge; lists good qualities; also includes fault of one as being "too easy with the Negroes"; both have small families.
      - Philip Brooks, Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesvill [sic], Louisa County, Virginia, 10 August 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Reports loss of his wife; expects to leave position within the year; refers to splitting of estate between William and Francis Jerdone; other business.
      - Francis Jerdone [Jr.], New Kent [County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 18 August 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Explains his reasons for having advertised for a manager on his brother's behalf.
      - Philip Brooks, Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 19 August 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Explains that he can't move West at a later time; proposes he stay on until following crop; family will be smaller; discusses wages.
      - Philip Brooks, "Providence Forge," [New Kent County. Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 27 August 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Refers to completion of list of stock and slaves for the forge and estate in Charles City; refers to move West; reports on crops; other family news.
      - W. Beazly, White Hall, [Spotsylvania County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 29 August 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Notifies that bond for Joe's hire has been sent though "it is not customary for me to send funds by negroes"; requests notice of receipt.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 13 October 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Writes that he's in solitary confinement and begs Jerdone to come and see him; requests his wife come, too.
      - John N. Moss, n.p. to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 29 October 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Reports went to courthouse in reference to sundry cases and the situation of bail; discusses details of legal matters.
      - Mary B. Moss, Mill Creek to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 7 November 1835., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Expresses deep affection for William Jerdone; refers to the slanderous remarks about her treatment of her niece which she hopes will be recognized as false.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, Francis Jerdone [Jr.], "Providence Forge," New Kent County, [Virginia], 9 November 1835., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Refers to process of acknowledgement of property [by new owners]; reports on crops and prices; refers to travels by Clayton Coleman; refers to plans of various individuals to move to Alabama and Arkansas; refers to accident of Tom Mitchell's brother, William; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, Providence Forge, [New Kent County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 9 November 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Refers to efforts to construct a smokehouse and details of construction; refers to how long he will stay; discusses crops, prices, and business.
      - John Jerdone, [Spo]tsylvania [County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 14 November 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Expresses disappointment in not having seen William on his trip; encourages him to write while he's away; refers to business.
      - Jno. Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Richmond, [Virginia], 4 December 1835., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:3)
        Not surprised at disappointment over sawyers and carpenters; refers to disagreement between William and brother Frank over division of estate; other family news.
    - Letters, 1836., 32 items. (Box-folder 8:4)
      - Samuel Wright, Bowling Green, Caroline County, Virginia to William Jerdone, New Kent Court House, Virginia, 12 January 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Refers to construction work Jerdone plans on having done; expresses great interest in taking on job.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Roxbury, via New Kent Court House, [Virginia], 31 January 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Discusses health of family, weather and crops; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 13 February 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Discusses weather; relates story of death of "Dick Luck"; refers to severe cold; discusses business and work done on the estate; other family news.
      - Samuel Wright, Bowling Green, Caroline County, Virginia to William Jerdone, New Kent Court House, Virginia, 16 February 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Expresses disagreement in building a log house; feels It is not worth his time; relates details of contract.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Roxbury, Virginia, 24 February 1836., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Reports weather and crops; expresses approval on course of action against W. Shell; other family news.
      - Samuel Wright, near Bowling Green, Caroline County, Virginia to William Jerdone, New Kent Court House, Virginia, 20 March 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Explains his delay because of the weather; promises to arrive as soon as possible.
      - Ch[arle]s Thompson, Thompson's Store, Han[over County, Virginia?] to his uncle, Francis Jerdone Sr., Louisa County, [Virginia], 21 March 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Relates death of his father, Charles Thompson; sends overseer and two hands to dig grave; asks to have location of mother's grave pointed out so father can be buried next to it.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County, Virginia], 13 April 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Discusses plans for approval of estates including appraiser's names, charge and suggestions; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone Sr., Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent, Virginia, 14 April 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Refers to John Jerdone's appraisal of his estate; discusses livestock; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], n.p. to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 27 April 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Relates death of grandson; refers to John's appraisal; gives advice on livestock and crops; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone, n.p. to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 8 May 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Discusses the progress of the appraisal; refers to the appraisal of the "Hell Swamp" to settle the debt of William Holt to Sarah Macon Jerdone and Francis Jerdone Sr.; gives appraisal of slaves; other family news.
      - Estimate of land holdings, negroes and estates of the Jerdone family and proportionate division among family members, 26 May 1836. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Drawn up by Fred[erick] Harris, C. Y. Kimbrough, and Charles Thompson, sent to Francis Jerdone sen[io]r.
      - Mary D. Cosby, Richmond, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, New Kent Court House, [Virginia], 6 June 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Apologizes for his disappointment and refers to plans for him to pick up his things any time.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent County, Virginia, 3 July 1836., ALS. 1 page. (Box-folder 8:4)
        Refers to discussion with father of dividing the estate; plans to move his share of slaves from forge; refers to weather and other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s City, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 5 August 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: crops, Improvements on estate, sales.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s City [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 17 August 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Reports on corn crop and attempts to sell it; refers to cotton; refers to well-being of slaves; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 30 August 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: crops, prices; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 3 September 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Thanks him for the watermelons; proposes going to Richmond together.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 6 September 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: delivery of crops, prices, health of slaves; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, Ch[arle]s City, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 28 September 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: begin to make bricks, crops, prices; other family news.
      - Mary B. Moss, Louisa [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 29 September 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Informs him of the health of Phillis [sic].
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 4 October 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: making bricks, picking cotton, and delivering corn; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 October 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Refers to family health; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s City, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 21 October 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: making bricks, crops, livestock; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 24 October 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses business: crops, sales; other family news.
      - W. Beazley, "White Hall," Spotsylvania [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 4 November 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Agrees to price for 8 servant's hire for coming year.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent County, Virginia, 24 November 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Discusses damages of a slave; refers to brother's new daughter; refers to health; discusses crops; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania [County, Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent County, Virginia, 28 November 1836., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Refers to high price of hogs; relates Idea of buying offal [such as heads and chine] of hogs and feeding the slaves with it; refers to railroads; reports birth of a daughter; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Richmond, [Virginia], 16 December 1836., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Refers to John's purchase of hogs; refers to John's filling his ice house; lists goods desired from Richmond; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 24 December 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Refers to pork he bought; reports illness of family prevents him from visiting; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 25 December 1836., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:5)
        Thanks for the oysters; refers to health of family; other family news.
    - Letters, 1837., 17 items. (Box-folder 8:6)
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent, Virginia, 15 January 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Describes health; refers to crop prices; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent, Virginia, 23 January 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Discusses family's health; refers to weather; refers to bond of Charles Thompson; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 17 February 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Discusses family health; refers to weather; reports operation of railroad and its route; discusses reasons for high price for slaves; refers to smallpox outbreak; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his brother, William Jerdone, Richmond, [Virginia], 25 March 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to Maria's accident and death of slaves; reports on crops; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Ch[arle]s City [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 2 April 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Reports on death and illness of slaves; refers to health of family; reports on crops and prices; other family news.
      - A[pperson] Dunton, n.p. to Francis Jerdone [Sr.], n.p., 20 April 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Reports death of sister Mary [Jerdone] Toler and funeral arrangements.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 25 April 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to William's loss of Negroes; reports death of Aunt [Mary Jerdone Pottie] Toler and arrangements for burial; discusses weather; reports on crops and animals; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], [Louisa County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 9 May 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to John's gift to his brothers of two homesick slaves; reports on weather and slow progress of fruit; other family news.
      - Francis Jerdone [Sr.], Louisa [County, Virginia] to his son, William Jerdone, Roxbury, New Kent [County], Virginia, 20 June 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to "Hilpik"s [Helpit?] death; discusses weather and crops; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Charles C[ity] County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 6 July 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Relates condition of crops; has been cutting grain; refers to death of a mule; refers to health of slaves.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his brother, William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 17 July 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to [brother] Frank's poor health; reports began cutting oats; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, New Kent County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 23 July 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Informs him [William Jerdone] that he intends to quit; outlines terms for his leaving; reports on health of slaves and condition of crops; other family news.
      - Mary B. Moss, Mill Creek, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 30 July 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Discusses health of Maria [Jerdone]; refers to Maria Coleman's affliction of worms; other family news.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," Charles C[ity] County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 11 August 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Discusses sale of corn and other business; refers to daughter [Maria's] health; other business news.
      - J. Stamps, New Kent [County, Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa [County], Virginia, 14 September 1837., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Introduces himself and applies to become manager of estate.
      - Philip Brooks, "Mount Sterling," C[hales] City County, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 17 September 1837., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 8:6)
        Refers to health of family; reports on crops and shortage of hands to son; refers to sale of his possessions; other family news.